<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/">
    <channel>
        <title>Erin's Portfolio Blog</title>
        <link>https://ecase6.github.io/erin-ui-portfolio2/blog</link>
        <description>Erin's Portfolio Blog</description>
        <lastBuildDate>Fri, 25 Oct 2024 15:30:00 GMT</lastBuildDate>
        <docs>https://validator.w3.org/feed/docs/rss2.html</docs>
        <generator>https://github.com/jpmonette/feed</generator>
        <language>en</language>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Debriefing User Tests]]></title>
            <link>https://ecase6.github.io/erin-ui-portfolio2/blog/debriefingUserTests</link>
            <guid>https://ecase6.github.io/erin-ui-portfolio2/blog/debriefingUserTests</guid>
            <pubDate>Fri, 25 Oct 2024 15:30:00 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[In response to Don't Make Me Think pages 137-141]]></description>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p><em>In response to Don't Make Me Think pages 137-141</em></p>
<p>On these pages, Krug talks about what usually goes wrong during user testing, and more importantly, how to fix it. It turns out most of the issues are simpler than we'd imagine. Some include:</p>
<ul>
<li>
<p>Users don’t get it. Sometimes, people just look at your site and are completely lost. Either they can’t figure out what it’s for, or they think they know and they’re totally wrong.</p>
</li>
<li>
<p>They can’t find the right words. They’re searching for something, but the words on your site don’t match what they’d expect.</p>
</li>
<li>
<p>Too much clutter. Ever had what you need right in front of you but you just couldn’t see it? That happens to users too. When there’s too much going on, people can miss what’s important. Sometimes the solution is to simplify the page or make key elements stand out more.</p>
</li>
</ul>
<p>After each round of testing, Krug recommends a quick debrief, ideally over pizza, to decide what needs fixing. The idea is to focus on the biggest problems first and avoid getting distracted by minor things. Here’s his approach:</p>
<ul>
<li>
<p>List the top issues. Go around the room and have everyone share what they saw as the three biggest problems. Write them down—no discussion yet, just listing them.</p>
</li>
<li>
<p>Prioritize. Once you’ve got the list, pick the ten most important problems and rank them from worst to least urgent.</p>
</li>
<li>
<p>Create a plan. For each of the top problems, figure out how you’ll fix it, who will handle it, and what resources they’ll need. The goal isn’t to fix every problem perfectly, but to make enough progress that the big issues are no longer deal-breakers.</p>
</li>
</ul>
<p>Krug’s advice is also to resist the urge to add more stuff when users are confused. Instead of piling on explanations, sometimes the best solution is to take things away and make the page simpler. And if a user suggests a new feature, take it with a grain of salt because they’ll often realize that they wouldn’t even use it themselves.</p>
<p><img decoding="async" loading="lazy" alt="Error getting image" src="https://ecase6.github.io/erin-ui-portfolio2/assets/images/perspective-0e578c587e97c1ba26fb2a506367982d.jpeg" width="5568" height="3712" class="img_ev3q"></p>]]></content:encoded>
            <category>FreeForm</category>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[User Testing 101]]></title>
            <link>https://ecase6.github.io/erin-ui-portfolio2/blog/userTesting101</link>
            <guid>https://ecase6.github.io/erin-ui-portfolio2/blog/userTesting101</guid>
            <pubDate>Fri, 25 Oct 2024 15:30:00 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[In response to Don't Make Me Think Chapters 8 and 9]]></description>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p><em>In response to Don't Make Me Think Chapters 8 and 9</em></p>
<p>If I had to choose one word to capture Chapter 8, it would be "Perspective". This chapter highlights how our professional and personal perspectives shape, and often complicate, our approach to usability in design. Designers, developers, marketers, and all other roles bring their own strong beliefs about what makes a great user experience. This can often clashing over details based on what matters most to them. For designers, it might be the visual aesthetic of a page, while for developers, it’s the clever and efficient functionality. And because we’re all technology users, we tend to project our preferences onto others, assuming other people want what we like.</p>
<p>This concept of perspective is important for me to remember in my career because it emphasizes the importance of staying open-minded. Recognizing different perspectives helps shift the focus from what I or others think users want to what users actually need. That’s where usability testing becomes essential. By stepping outside of our personal viewpoints, we can rely on user feedback to ground our designs in real-world use. This perspective shift can make decisions easier and lead to better, more user-focused designs that work for everyone.</p>
<p><img decoding="async" loading="lazy" alt="Error getting image" src="https://ecase6.github.io/erin-ui-portfolio2/assets/images/testing-56846d51d4d5c7e5bdadf8b8694cf25f.jpeg" width="6720" height="2992" class="img_ev3q"></p>]]></content:encoded>
            <category>WordJournal</category>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Feedback Workshop]]></title>
            <link>https://ecase6.github.io/erin-ui-portfolio2/blog/feedback</link>
            <guid>https://ecase6.github.io/erin-ui-portfolio2/blog/feedback</guid>
            <pubDate>Thu, 17 Oct 2024 15:30:00 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[In response to https://www.invisionapp.com/inside-design/give-designers-feedback/]]></description>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p><em>In response to <a href="https://www.invisionapp.com/inside-design/give-designers-feedback/" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">https://www.invisionapp.com/inside-design/give-designers-feedback/</a></em></p>
<p>Providing feedback to designers is like giving instructions to a chef. If you say, “Make me something delicious,” the chef has to guess what you like, and the result might not align with your expectations. However, if you’re clear and specific, the chef has the guidance needed to create something that satisfies your taste and dietary needs. Just as a chef benefits from understanding your preferences and restrictions, a designer needs actionable and detailed feedback to craft a design that matches your vision.</p>
<p>Designers, much like chefs, work with “ingredients”: color palettes, typography, layouts, user interactions, etc. These elements can be combined in lots of ways, and without guidance, a designer may produce work that doesn’t fully meet your goals or needs. Just as vague feedback leaves a chef guessing, it leaves a designer uncertain about your expectations. Precise feedback, on the other hand, empowers both the chef and the designer to make creative choices that are aligned with the intended outcome.</p>
<p>As I prepare to transition into a full-time career in software development, the importance of effective communication is becoming increasingly clear. Whether I’m collaborating with designers, other developers, or stakeholders, being able to provide meaningful feedback will be critical. When working with designers in particular, understanding how to deliver feedback that is specific, constructive, and tied to project goals can make all the difference.</p>
<p><img decoding="async" loading="lazy" alt="Error getting image" src="https://ecase6.github.io/erin-ui-portfolio2/assets/images/feedback-64b30f78e59b1f9dc216ac12fdc5d8ea.jpeg" width="6551" height="2290" class="img_ev3q"></p>]]></content:encoded>
            <category>ApproximateAnalogy</category>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Mockups]]></title>
            <link>https://ecase6.github.io/erin-ui-portfolio2/blog/mockups</link>
            <guid>https://ecase6.github.io/erin-ui-portfolio2/blog/mockups</guid>
            <pubDate>Thu, 17 Oct 2024 15:30:00 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[In response to Don't Make Me Think Chapter 7 and Presentation Zen Chapters 2 and 4]]></description>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p><em>In response to Don't Make Me Think Chapter 7 and Presentation Zen Chapters 2 and 4</em></p>
<p>In Chapter 7 of Don’t Make Me Think, Krug highlights the importance of a seamless and intuitive user experience. One of the main takeaways is the concept of "the first law of usability," which states that a user interface should be self-evident. This means that users shouldn’t have to think too much to understand how something works; they should be able to glance at a webpage or an app and know immediately what to do. This principle is central to creating effective digital experiences because it reduces cognitive load and frustration. This allows users to focus on their goals rather than trying to figure out confusing navigation or design elements.</p>
<p>On the other hand, Presentation Zen (Chapters 2 and 4) by Reynolds focuses on effective presentation design, with an emphasis on simplicity and storytelling. In Chapter 2, Reynolds introduces the idea of "restraint" in design, using only what is necessary to convey your message without overwhelming your audience with excessive text, data, etc. Chapter 4 expands on this by discussing the importance of visual clarity and the power of storytelling. A compelling narrative paired with clean, minimal slides can make presentations more engaging.</p>
<p>When we merge these ideas from both books, the ideas of simplicity, clarity, and engagement are apparent, whether you're designing a user interface or delivering a presentation. In both cases, the goal is to guide your audience without distracting or confusing them. Just as Krug advises designers to create user interfaces that don't require thought, Reynolds advises presenters to strip away unnecessary clutter so that the core message stands out.</p>
<p>As someone working in software development, these lessons are incredibly relevant. Whether I’m collaborating on a UI project or preparing a presentation, balancing simplicity and engagement will be important. In user interface design, I’ve learned that every additional button, menu, or piece of text is a potential point of confusion for the user. The more straightforward the interface, the easier it will be for the user to accomplish their goals.</p>
<p><img decoding="async" loading="lazy" alt="Error getting image" src="https://ecase6.github.io/erin-ui-portfolio2/assets/images/clarity-98ab9934ab82a1212494ce1514df4adf.jpeg" width="2688" height="1792" class="img_ev3q"></p>]]></content:encoded>
            <category>FreeForm</category>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Portfolios & Design Narratives]]></title>
            <link>https://ecase6.github.io/erin-ui-portfolio2/blog/PortfoliosAndDesignNarratives</link>
            <guid>https://ecase6.github.io/erin-ui-portfolio2/blog/PortfoliosAndDesignNarratives</guid>
            <pubDate>Tue, 15 Oct 2024 15:30:00 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[In response to https://blog.uxfol.io/ux-portfolio-examples/]]></description>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p><em>In response to <a href="https://blog.uxfol.io/ux-portfolio-examples/" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">https://blog.uxfol.io/ux-portfolio-examples/</a></em></p>
<p>This piece does a good job at demonstrating how each of the portfolios are unique and show off the designer's individuality, but still manages to be consistent and easy to use. Each designer has their own style, creativity, and perspective, which helps communicate who they are and what they're all about. Even though the designs are different, they all follow good usability practices, making it easy for viewers to navigate and understand the content.</p>
<p>This balance between individuality and consistency is very important for UX portfolios. It lets designers express their unique approach while making sure the portfolio is still accessible and user-friendly. Consistent navigation, typography, and structure create a familiar experience for viewers, while unique visual elements, color schemes, and personal touches make the portfolio stand out and be memorable.</p>
<p>For my career, I think it's important to remember that a good portfolio isn't just about showing off creativity, it's also about making sure the user experience is smooth and easy. By combining both individuality and consistency, I can create a portfolio that not only grabs attention but also communicates my design skills and thought process effectively.</p>
<p><img decoding="async" loading="lazy" alt="Error getting image" src="https://ecase6.github.io/erin-ui-portfolio2/assets/images/lightbulb-e0cf0380b243ca1d412274b4421736a3.jpeg" width="6000" height="2500" class="img_ev3q"></p>]]></content:encoded>
            <category>FreeForm</category>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Navigation and Values]]></title>
            <link>https://ecase6.github.io/erin-ui-portfolio2/blog/navigationAndValues</link>
            <guid>https://ecase6.github.io/erin-ui-portfolio2/blog/navigationAndValues</guid>
            <pubDate>Tue, 08 Oct 2024 15:30:00 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[In response to Chapter 6 of An Exercise for Individuals and Teams.” Colin Breck's Blog, 2 Feb. 2020]]></description>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p><em>In response to Chapter 6 of: Krug, S. (2006). Don't make me think! A common sense approach to web usability (2nd ed.). New Riders. and Breck, Colin. “Understanding Our Core Values: An Exercise for Individuals and Teams.” Colin Breck's Blog, 2 Feb. 2020</em></p>
<p>In Don't Make Me Think, Chapter 6, Steve Krug emphasizes the importance of making web design intuitive. With good design, users should be able to easily navigate without stopping to figure out what to do. The word that perfectly sums this up is "clarity." To me, this means more than just good design - it also is about how we communicate, solve problems, and collaborate.</p>
<p>When I read about core values in Colin Breck’s blog, the same idea of clarity stood out. Clear communication and transparent values help teams work smoothly, just like how clear design helps users move effortlessly through a website. It’s about reducing the mental load, whether for users or colleagues, so they can focus on what really matters.</p>
<p>In my career as a software engineer, I know how important it is to keep things clear, whether it’s in code, documentation, or interface design. Without clarity, people get stuck, frustrated, or lost. By sticking to this value in my work, I’ll not only make better products but also contribute to stronger, more effective teams.</p>
<p>Whether I’m building an app or collaborating with a team, I want everything to be straightforward and easy to understand. That way, we can focus on creating great experiences and solving real problems.</p>
<p><img decoding="async" loading="lazy" alt="Error getting image" src="https://ecase6.github.io/erin-ui-portfolio2/assets/images/balance-ccc2ec75f9e71603b5b06c0a4663412c.jpeg" width="3600" height="2395" class="img_ev3q"></p>]]></content:encoded>
            <category>WordJournal</category>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Finding Inspiration]]></title>
            <link>https://ecase6.github.io/erin-ui-portfolio2/blog/findingInspiration</link>
            <guid>https://ecase6.github.io/erin-ui-portfolio2/blog/findingInspiration</guid>
            <pubDate>Fri, 04 Oct 2024 15:30:00 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[Error getting image]]></description>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p><img decoding="async" loading="lazy" alt="Error getting image" src="https://ecase6.github.io/erin-ui-portfolio2/assets/images/hotdog-4bb5011a1de38ad641c20befb10325db.jpg" width="2598" height="2037" class="img_ev3q"></p>
<p>The art piece I found inspiration in is Hot Dog Bridge by Russell T. Gordon. This is a six-color lithograph created in 1974 and is part of the University of Nebraska–Lincoln's collection, gifted by Dr. Christopher and Janet Graf. Gordon, an American artist, was born in Philadelphia in 1936 and later passed in Montreal in 2013. The artwork portrays a surreal scene where a hot dog stretches across two canyon-like formations, set against a vivid background featuring a bright blue sky, white clouds, and a rainbow. This whimsical combination of elements evokes nostalgia, inviting viewers to embrace humor and lightheartedness during challenging times.</p>
<p><strong>Analysis</strong></p>
<ol>
<li>Color Balance</li>
</ol>
<p>The vibrant color palette used in Hot Dog Bridge immediately grabs attention. The contrast between the bright blue sky, the bold rainbow, and the warm tones of the rocks creates a balanced and dynamic visual experience. The hot dog, an iconic and familiar object, stands out against the surreal background and magnifies the humor in the piece. The combination of these bold and simplified colors creates a whimsical and dreamlike atmosphere.</p>
<p><em>The above ideas are influenced by Joseph Albers’ Interaction of Color, which discusses the importance of contrast in evoking emotion through colors.</em></p>
<ol start="2">
<li>Surrealism and Humor</li>
</ol>
<p>At first glance, the piece's absurdity is what draws you in. A hot dog spanning a canyon is not a typical sight. This constract between reality and imagination is central to surrealism. It encourages people to find meaning in the nonsensical, which is exactly what happened for me while viewing this piece. The surreal nature of the work, paired with its lighthearted humor, represents a comforting escape from ther seriousness and challenges of the "real-world".</p>
<p><em>The above ideas are influenced by Salvador Dalí’s works, which often use juxtaposition to inspire thought beyond the obvious.</em></p>
<ol start="3">
<li>Simplicity of Forms</li>
</ol>
<p>Gordon's use of clean, simplified shapes, like geometric clouds, smooth curves of the hot dog, and blocky rocks creates a unified look that is easy to process visually. Despite the bizarre concept, the clarity and simplicity of the forms make it accessible to viewers. This is a prime example of how minimalistic design choices can strengthen the overall impact of a surreal composition, allowing each element to stand out clearly.</p>
<p><em>The above ideas are influenced by Wassily Kandinsky's Point and Line to Plane, which offers insights into how basic forms and geometry influence perception in art.</em></p>
<p><strong>UI Sketch</strong></p>
<p><img decoding="async" loading="lazy" alt="Error getting image" src="https://ecase6.github.io/erin-ui-portfolio2/assets/images/hotdogUISketch-c34a84bc1f5379c13d755a73ca557c45.jpg" width="2302" height="2615" class="img_ev3q"></p>
<p>This hand-drawn sketch above represents a mobile app screen. The inspiration behind this idea was the way that I open up my notes app nearly every day to make quick to-do lists, often with only a couple of items. I thought it would be much more fun if my lists were more whimsy and playful, like this piece of art. So, the main functionality is a simple todo list, where the user drags the hot dog across the canyon once they complete a task, symbolizing the "bridge" of completing a task. So, the hot dog would start short and end up quite long.</p>
<p>I felt that displaying a hand-drawn sketch alone would not capture everything I was inspired by. Color, whim, surrealism, and humor were main aspects of my inspiration, so I did a quick design on Canva to try to convey the playful vibe I wanted to display, as color is very important to my thoughts on this.</p>
<p><img decoding="async" loading="lazy" alt="Error getting image" src="https://ecase6.github.io/erin-ui-portfolio2/assets/images/hotdogUI-bbfbf9480f16219f6b74a27935b431e8.png" width="584" height="1008" class="img_ev3q"></p>
<p>Through this process, I’ve learned how surrealist art can inspire UI design by embracing imagination and playfulness, even in something as simple and mundane as a to-do app. Using bold colors and simplifying forms allows a balance between creative inspiration and accessibility, making interfaces both functional and delightful.</p>]]></content:encoded>
            <category>FreeForm</category>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Design Systems]]></title>
            <link>https://ecase6.github.io/erin-ui-portfolio2/blog/designSystems</link>
            <guid>https://ecase6.github.io/erin-ui-portfolio2/blog/designSystems</guid>
            <pubDate>Mon, 30 Sep 2024 15:30:00 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[In response to various articles on designsystems.com]]></description>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p><em>In response to various articles on designsystems.com</em></p>
<p><strong>Design systems are to a well-organized library as the combination of spatial grids, typography, and content strategy are to the shelves, book arrangements, and catalog system.</strong></p>
<p>Each part of the design system plays an important role in making the library easy to navigate and efficient to use. Just as every component in a library needs to work together to create a positive user experience, the same applies to design systems.</p>
<p>In a library, spatial grids are like the well-spaced shelves and clearly defined aisles. They create a visual and physical structure that makes navigating easy. If the shelves are poorly arranged or spaced unevenly, it would be difficult for people to find their way. Similarly, in a design system, spatial grids ensure that the layout of elements is predictable and uniform across different pages and components. This allows users to navigate interfaces easily and reinforces trust in the product, similar to how visitors trust a well-organized library to fulfill its purpose. The <em>Space, Grids, and Layouts</em> article emphasizes how spatial systems create visual rhythm and help reduce decision-making for designers. This same idea is like how people in libraries don’t need to think about how the aisles are structured, they just follow the natural flow.</p>
<p>Typography is like the labels on books, shelves, and sections within the library. Good typography ensures that users can quickly understand what each section holds. In design, clear, readable fonts with well-defined hierarchies ensure that users can scan and read content easily. Just as a library with inconsistent labeling would confuse its visitors, a product with inconsistent typography would frustrate its users. In the <em>Typography</em> article, it’s noted how font choices, weights, and line-heights are critical in creating a consistent design language. For a designer, mastering typography means ensuring that every piece of text conveys the right tone and importance, just like how a library carefully chooses its signage to direct people.</p>
<p>Lastly, content strategy functions like the library’s cataloging system. It tells users where to find what they need, how to use the resources effectively, and what to expect in each section. Without a content strategy, users may feel lost or overwhelmed. For example, if books were organized randomly without a coherent strategy, finding information would be impossible. The <em>Guide to Content Strategy</em> article emphasizes how vital it is to standardize how content appears across different UI elements. In the same way that a library catalog makes finding information easier, a strong content strategy helps users understand and navigate interfaces.</p>
<p>Design systems bring order to chaos, just like a well-maintained library does. By understanding how spatial grids, typography, and content strategy work together, as a designer I'll be able to save time, reduce complexity, and provide a more intuitive experience for users. Consistency and ease of use directly impact a product’s success. These principles ensure that you’re building something that’s not just functional, but also scalable, like a well-architected library that can continue to grow without losing its organization.</p>
<p><img decoding="async" loading="lazy" alt="Error getting image" src="https://ecase6.github.io/erin-ui-portfolio2/assets/images/library-21224c69bfa9960f6c02619b39f0963e.jpeg" width="2993" height="2000" class="img_ev3q"></p>]]></content:encoded>
            <category>ApproximateAnalogy</category>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Color Study]]></title>
            <link>https://ecase6.github.io/erin-ui-portfolio2/blog/colorStudy</link>
            <guid>https://ecase6.github.io/erin-ui-portfolio2/blog/colorStudy</guid>
            <pubDate>Thu, 26 Sep 2024 15:30:00 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[The Drink Half Past website has a UI that stands out to me, and I'd like to take some time to study it and]]></description>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>The <em>Drink Half Past</em> website has a UI that stands out to me, and I'd like to take some time to study it and
experiment with the colors on the page.</p>
<p><img decoding="async" loading="lazy" alt="Error getting image" src="https://ecase6.github.io/erin-ui-portfolio2/assets/images/drinkHalfPast-9f9ecde9b6e701ff88334d0b144d8096.png" width="2870" height="1536" class="img_ev3q"></p>
<p>The original color scheme in the screenshot primarily uses pastel shades:</p>
<ul>
<li>Pink (Grapefruit with Rosemary)</li>
<li>Peachy orange (Ginger with Turmeric)</li>
<li>Soft green (Spicy Lime)</li>
<li>Light yellow (Pineapple with Clove)
These background colors are similar to the colors of the cans.</li>
</ul>
<p>The buttons at the bottom of each drink card are variations of green, blue, and purple (the same color as the labels on the can). The text is mainly black, with the product names using bold, block-like fonts in dark contrasting colors, making them stand out clearly.</p>
<p>This color scheme fits into a split complementary color scheme. Pastel shades of pink, green, yellow, and peach provide soft, harmonious contrasts while the bold colors of the text and cans create focal points. The color choices also feel fresh and organic, matching the natural, vibrant qualities the brand wants to communicate.</p>
<p>The designers seem to be going for a clean, fresh, and somewhat playful mood. The pastel tones feel light and refreshing, suggesting the natural flavors/ingredients in the drinks. The bold product names give an energetic vibe, helping to reinforce the feeling of excitement and adventure in trying new flavors.</p>
<p><strong>Recreation 1: Light Blue Monochromatic Scheme</strong>
<img decoding="async" loading="lazy" alt="Error getting image" src="https://ecase6.github.io/erin-ui-portfolio2/assets/images/halfPastUI1-db71ad4638a1b1e1c7547d305bd6fb8b.png" width="960" height="720" class="img_ev3q">
This version features soft, pastel-like blue tones across the entire design. The background of each flavor card uses light shades of blue with different levels of saturation, while the buttons and text follow a similar light color scheme.
It gives a calm, clean, and refreshing feel. The light blue tones evoke a sense of trust and reliability, making the design feel professional and safe. Its cool tones imply cooling and refreshing factors in the beverage. However, the lack of strong contrast between product cards might make it harder to differentiate between flavors at a glance. While it’s visually cohesive, it could feel a bit monotonous for users seeking variety in the product options.</p>
<p><strong>Recreation 2: Earthy Analogous Scheme</strong>
<img decoding="async" loading="lazy" alt="Error getting image" src="https://ecase6.github.io/erin-ui-portfolio2/assets/images/halfPastUI2-8bd7d8e3c86b1c2aba8da98b22e6b49f.png" width="960" height="720" class="img_ev3q">
This version uses a palette of greens and yellows. Each card features either a light yellow or green background, with slightly darker buttons to contrast. The analogous colors (adjacent on the color wheel) create a natural, harmonious vibe. This design has a very organic, earthy feel, which reflects the idea of natural ingredients and freshness. The yellow and green tones make it feel health-conscious and environmentally friendly. The analogous colors work well together, creating a balanced and cohesive look without clashing. This version is effective in emphasizing the natural qualities of the products but might lack the visual "pop" needed to grab users' attention quickly. It’s subtle and pleasing, but not as exciting as other schemes.</p>
<p><strong>Recreation 3: High-Contrast Complementary Scheme</strong>
<img decoding="async" loading="lazy" alt="Error getting image" src="https://ecase6.github.io/erin-ui-portfolio2/assets/images/halfPastUI3-344144ffd9e4a3074bbe4fdd0c1a9059.png" width="960" height="720" class="img_ev3q"></p>
<p>In this version, bright orange backgrounds are paired with blue accents for a bold, complementary color scheme. The contrast is striking, and the colors create a strong visual division between product sections. The orange and blue combination conveys energy, excitement, and urgency. This high-contrast scheme draws immediate attention and creates a dynamic, lively feel. It could be particularly effective in grabbing the attention of users who are quickly browsing the page. The complementary scheme is highly effective in making the UI engaging and attention-grabbing. However, the intensity of the colors may feel a bit overwhelming to some users, especially if they're used to more neutral designs. Still, for an energetic, adventurous brand, this could work very well.</p>
<p><strong>Recreation 4: Triadic Scheme</strong>
<img decoding="async" loading="lazy" alt="Error getting image" src="https://ecase6.github.io/erin-ui-portfolio2/assets/images/halfPastUI4-624e7225e0057f6abc0aa73a7ee1176e.png" width="960" height="720" class="img_ev3q">
The triadic scheme features a balance between purple, green, and yellow. Each product card has one of these three colors in a light, pastel tone, and the buttons use muted versions of the same colors to keep the palette consistent. This design feels playful and creative. The triadic color scheme keeps the page dynamic without the high tension of a complementary scheme. The colors are bright but not overpowering, giving a sense of fun and variety while maintaining balance. This scheme is effective in creating visual interest without overwhelming the user. It strikes a balance between contrast and harmony, making it one of the most engaging versions. It allows each product to stand out while still keeping a unified design. It could appeal to users looking for a fun, energetic brand experience.</p>
<p>Each color scheme has its strengths, but the Triadic Scheme (4) stands out as the most effective overall for the following reasons:</p>
<p>Variety/Balance: The triadic scheme offers visual variety while maintaining balance. It provides contrast without overwhelming the user, making the UI both dynamic and visually interesting.</p>
<p>Mood: The playful, vibrant tones fit the personality of a brand that sells unique and exciting beverages. It appeals to users' sense of curiosity and fun.</p>
<p>Functionality: The differentiation between each product card is clear, making it easy for users to distinguish between flavors while still feeling like the entire page is cohesive.</p>
<p>This scheme would likely be the most engaging for users while maintaining the product’s fresh and lively feel. It is the most similar to the original design, which I think is really great UI. In my version, though, I leaned into the triadic design more. However, this doesn't reflect the flavors as well as the original does.</p>
<p>While I don't think it's the most effective, I did love the boldness and edginess of Recreation 3. Everyone has their own opinions and taste!</p>]]></content:encoded>
            <category>FreeForm</category>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Colors I]]></title>
            <link>https://ecase6.github.io/erin-ui-portfolio2/blog/colorsI</link>
            <guid>https://ecase6.github.io/erin-ui-portfolio2/blog/colorsI</guid>
            <pubDate>Thu, 26 Sep 2024 15:30:00 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[In response to pages 8-25 of Expert color information for professional color results. Rockport Publishers.]]></description>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p><em>In response to pages 8-25 of: Sutton, T., &amp; Whelan, B. M. (1998). The complete color harmony: Expert color information for professional color results. Rockport Publishers.</em></p>
<p>I thought it would be interesting to try “The Process” on page 14.</p>
<p><strong>STEP 1:
Clearly define the results you want to achieve with color.</strong></p>
<p>I want to create something that invokes feelings of calmness, lightheartedness, ease, and playfulness.</p>
<p>This step was important because it made me really think about the emotions I wanted to create, reminding me that design is not just about looks - it's about how it makes people feel.</p>
<p><strong>STEP 2:
Select a main color that reflects the needs of the project.</strong></p>
<p>I chose blue since it's often associated with calmness and peacefulness. This part helped me see how selecting a color can set the tone for an entire project, much like how a project's main goal drives design choices.</p>
<p><strong>STEP 3:
Select a color scheme based on the choice of the central hue.</strong></p>
<p><img decoding="async" loading="lazy" alt="Error getting image" src="https://ecase6.github.io/erin-ui-portfolio2/assets/images/blue-d429d92635b27383ec1552e55cda2283.png" width="856" height="248" class="img_ev3q"></p>
<p>After experimenting with different palettes, I realized how much the surrounding colors can affect the mood. Blue paired with lighter, pastel tones felt lighthearted and playful, while pairing it with deeper hues added a sense of balance and seriousness.</p>
<p><strong>STEP 4:
Refine the available color choices in terms of the particular project or individual sensibility.</strong></p>
<p>I narrowed it down to three colors, which made the scheme feel more focused and simple. This step made me think about constraints. If this were a real project, I would need to consider factors like accessibility and brand identity. Simplifying the palette was a valuable exercise in making choices that align with the project's goals.</p>
<p><img decoding="async" loading="lazy" alt="Error getting image" src="https://ecase6.github.io/erin-ui-portfolio2/assets/images/3colors-e64e771e9e802f9f15be48b07121bd7f.png" width="2298" height="534" class="img_ev3q"></p>
<p>Reflection: Going through this process gave me insight into how color can shape a user's experience. In my future career as a software engineer, this will be useful when designing user interfaces. I see how important it is to start by defining the emotional goals of a project, then select colors thoughtfully to support those goals. Narrowing down a palette to just a few colors will keep the design clean and user-friendly, which is key in building intuitive software. This exercise showed me that every color choice should be intentional, creating a visual experience that reflects the project's purpose.</p>]]></content:encoded>
            <category>FreeForm</category>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Colors II]]></title>
            <link>https://ecase6.github.io/erin-ui-portfolio2/blog/colorsII</link>
            <guid>https://ecase6.github.io/erin-ui-portfolio2/blog/colorsII</guid>
            <pubDate>Thu, 26 Sep 2024 15:30:00 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[In response to pages 26-55 and 176-191 of Expert color information for professional color results. Rockport Publishers.]]></description>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p><em>In response to pages 26-55 and 176-191 of: Sutton, T., &amp; Whelan, B. M. (1998). The complete color harmony: Expert color information for professional color results. Rockport Publishers.</em></p>
<p>Reading about the different types of color schemes at the beginning of this section of the book immediately made
me think of the schemes that I gravitate towards. I really enjoy clash and complementary schemes, and I found examples
of both of these on posters I have hung up in my room. Not only have I seen these schemes in my posters, but I've also
seen them in lots of other decor and even some UI.</p>
<p><img decoding="async" loading="lazy" alt="Error getting image" src="https://ecase6.github.io/erin-ui-portfolio2/assets/images/freePoster-d4a8de99ee251194ccba3fafb86ad150.jpg" width="2635" height="3460" class="img_ev3q"></p>
<p>The above poster has a mix of muted green and blue with big red letters that jump out aggressively. This is a prime example of what’s known as a clash scheme—where colors that aren't quite opposites on the color wheel create visual tension. The green and blue of the background sit comfortably together, but the red stands out. It’s bold, unexpected, and it demands attention.</p>
<p>In UI design, clash schemes can be powerful but intense. They demand attention. I can think of a button in an app that’s an intense color against a muted background. This kind of contrast can drive action, but it can also overwhelm the user. I think the trick would be to use clashing colors intentionally, in small amounts, to direct the user’s focus without causing discomfort or cognitive overload.</p>
<p><img decoding="async" loading="lazy" alt="Error getting image" src="https://ecase6.github.io/erin-ui-portfolio2/assets/images/tylerPoster-be12709bf41e5761558033f4bb58c42b.jpg" width="2458" height="3446" class="img_ev3q"></p>
<p>In this other poster, above, it is dominated by blue, with a man in a yellow suit. This follows a complementary color scheme. Blue and yellow sit opposite each other on the color wheel, creating a nice, unique balance. This type of scheme is great for catching the eye while maintaining a sense of cohesion and calm. The yellow suit pops against the blue background, but in a way that feels less confrontational than the clash of red, green, and blue in the first poster.</p>
<p>In UI design, complementary colors can help create emphasis without overwhelming the user. A blue interface with strategically placed yellow elements—buttons, icons, or text would be a good idea. It’s like giving them visual cues without shouting.</p>
<p>My posters will be a reminder of how different color schemes evoke different emotions. Clash schemes can create excitement, urgency, or even discomfort when needed, but must be used carefully. They’re great for making something stand out, like error messages or call-to-action buttons, but too much can overwhelm users. On the other hand, complementary schemes offer contrast in a way that’s pleasing to the eye. This balance is ideal for creating interfaces that feel both engaging and easy to navigate. When users are working through a complex app or website, they don’t want to feel like they’re being bombarded with too much intensity. Complementary colors offer that subtle touch.</p>
<p>Both posters and both color schemes have their place. I think that the key to UI, much like in art, is knowing which tool to use at the right moment.</p>]]></content:encoded>
            <category>FreeForm</category>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Aesthetic Design]]></title>
            <link>https://ecase6.github.io/erin-ui-portfolio2/blog/aestheticDesign</link>
            <guid>https://ecase6.github.io/erin-ui-portfolio2/blog/aestheticDesign</guid>
            <pubDate>Fri, 20 Sep 2024 15:30:00 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[In response to Chapter 6 of Simple ideas on presentation design and delivery. New Riders.]]></description>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p><em>In response to Chapter 6 of: Reynolds, G. (2008). <em>Presentation Zen: Simple ideas on presentation design and delivery</em>. New Riders.</em></p>
<p>After reading about "The Big Four" design principles—Contrast, Repetition, Alignment, and Proximity in the reading, I thought about ways these ideas are common in life that have nothing to do with screens or the internet.</p>
<p>For example: contrast. This principle is everywhere, like when picking out an outfit. Wearing a black or neutral colored dress with a red bag/accessory makes the red stand out and adds interest to the look. The reading emphasized how contrast helps important elements pop, which is the same reason why we might pair a bold accessory with a simple outfit.</p>
<p>Repetition is a big part of interior design, like in the way a cozy room might have the same vibe of decor or the same color throughout the space. This creates a sense of unity, just as the book describes.</p>
<p>Alignment made me think about hanging up pictures to create a “gallery wall”. When things are lined up intentionally, it instantly makes the space look more organized and visually pleasing. The reading pointed out how alignment brings order to a design, which is why we naturally line things up in our surroundings, it just feels right.</p>
<p>Lastly, proximity made me think of arranging items on a kitchen counter. We instinctively group things that go together, like coffee mugs next to the coffee maker or utensils close to the stove. The reading’s point about proximity helping to show relationships between items clicked with me when I thought of how we organize our physical spaces to be more functional.</p>
<p>Understanding these principles will definitely help in my future as a software engineer. When designing software, applying contrast, repetition, alignment, and proximity can make an app’s layout as cohesive as outfits or gallery walls. It’s all about creating an experience that feels natural and easy to navigate, just like how we arrange things in our everyday spaces.</p>
<p><img decoding="async" loading="lazy" alt="Error getting image" src="https://ecase6.github.io/erin-ui-portfolio2/assets/images/redBag-ffa079836edea1ce6a26196af0233961.jpeg" width="6971" height="4647" class="img_ev3q"></p>]]></content:encoded>
            <category>FreeForm</category>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Design Rules]]></title>
            <link>https://ecase6.github.io/erin-ui-portfolio2/blog/designRules</link>
            <guid>https://ecase6.github.io/erin-ui-portfolio2/blog/designRules</guid>
            <pubDate>Fri, 13 Sep 2024 15:30:00 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[In response to Chapters 2, 3, 4, and 5 of: Krug, S. (2006). Don't make me think! A common sense approach to web usability (2nd ed.). New Riders.]]></description>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p><em>In response to Chapters 2, 3, 4, and 5 of: Krug, S. (2006). Don't make me think! A common sense approach to web usability (2nd ed.). New Riders.</em></p>
<p>Scanning and Satisficing from Chapter 2 emphasize that users don’t consume information in a linear way, or read everything. This is why Visual Hierarchy (Chapter 3) and the use of Conventions are important. If a website or app follows established patterns, it makes it easier for users to look through and find what they need.</p>
<p>The relationship between Navigation Clarity (Chapter 4) and Visual Hierarchy (Chapter 3) is crucial. A well-designed hierarchy can improve navigation by highlighting what's important and where users need to go (e.g., having breadcrumbs). Together, these help users feel in control and avoid getting lost.</p>
<p>Minimizing unnecessary text (Chapter 5) works hand-in-hand with reducing visual noise (Chapter 3). This combination helps reduce cognitive load, making it easier for users to process content quickly without being overwhelmed. Clickability from Chapter 3 also ties into this, as clear, concise instructions should guide users to the right actions.</p>
<p>Across all chapters, Krug reinforces that the core focus should always be usability, whether through simplifying text, improving navigation, or designing with conventions in mind. Each chapter adds another layer to this, highlighting that the easier we make it for users, the more successful the product will be.</p>
<p>Understanding these relationships is important to create user-friendly apps/websites. By internalizing how users think and interact with digital products, I'll be able to design solutions that reduce frustration, improve engagement, and lead to better overall satisfaction. Whether I'm developing a database or designing a feature in my future software engineering work, these ideas will be helpful while trying to create intuitive, effective solutions.</p>
<p><img decoding="async" loading="lazy" alt="Error getting image" src="https://ecase6.github.io/erin-ui-portfolio2/assets/images/hierarchy-01abe34988eb6831e061c832c290bc97.jpeg" width="5824" height="3264" class="img_ev3q"></p>]]></content:encoded>
            <category>FreeForm</category>
            <category>ConceptMap</category>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Schneiderman & Info Org]]></title>
            <link>https://ecase6.github.io/erin-ui-portfolio2/blog/schneidermanAndInfoOrg</link>
            <guid>https://ecase6.github.io/erin-ui-portfolio2/blog/schneidermanAndInfoOrg</guid>
            <pubDate>Fri, 06 Sep 2024 15:30:00 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[In response to Shneiderman, B. (1996). The eyes have it//doi.org/10.1109/VL.1996.545307]]></description>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p><em>In response to Shneiderman, B. (1996). The eyes have it: A task by data type taxonomy for information visualizations. Proceedings of the IEEE Symposium on Visual Languages, 336–343. <a href="https://doi.org/10.1109/VL.1996.545307" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">https://doi.org/10.1109/VL.1996.545307</a></em></p>
<p>The "Visual Information-Seeking Mantra" is to data as a GPS is to navigation.</p>
<p>Just like a GPS helps you get an overview of your surroundings, zoom into specific areas, filter out routes and provide more details when needed, the mantra ("Overview first, zoom and filter, then details on demand") is a guide for navigating large datasets. It helps users to gain an overall understanding, find and process relevant information, and get specific details when needed.</p>
<p>This concept is important for my career because, as a software engineer, I will almost certainly at some point need to present complex or large amounts of data in an easily digestible format. Just as GPS makes traveling simpler by removing the complexity of maps, applying this mantra to visualizing/formatting data would make reviewing large datasets more manageable and efficient for users.</p>
<p><img decoding="async" loading="lazy" alt="Error getting image" src="https://ecase6.github.io/erin-ui-portfolio2/assets/images/phoneGPS-af5ecc120cc3bab12b6751c6f76d5c9c.jpeg" width="6000" height="4000" class="img_ev3q"></p>]]></content:encoded>
            <category>ApproximateAnalogy</category>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Affordances & Signifiers II]]></title>
            <link>https://ecase6.github.io/erin-ui-portfolio2/blog/affordancesAndSignifiersII</link>
            <guid>https://ecase6.github.io/erin-ui-portfolio2/blog/affordancesAndSignifiersII</guid>
            <pubDate>Tue, 03 Sep 2024 15:30:00 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[In response to Chapter 2 of: Norman, D.A. (2013). The design of everyday things. MIT Press.]]></description>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p><em>In response to Chapter 2 of: Norman, D.A. (2013). The design of everyday things. MIT Press.</em></p>
<p>I read Chapter 2 of DOET while having <em>RuPaul's Drag Race</em> on in the background, and I found there are some connections I can draw between the two.</p>
<p>The ideas of the "Gulf of Execution" and the "Seven Stages of Action" can be seen in the creative process of drag queens on RuPaul's Drag Race. Queens will usually start with a clear goal for challenges and runways (like embodying a specific character or theme) but sometimes things are lost between intention and execution. Just as DOET describes, they must plan, execute, and then evaluate their actions, adjusting based on feedback. The "Gulf of Execution" becomes evident when their vision doesn’t fully translate into their look or performance, which demonstrates the challenges of transforming an idea into reality.</p>
<p>This reflection on the stages of action and the gap between intention and outcome shows the complex process of design, whether in drag or in design of everyday objects. I'll keep this in mind when I'm designing or developing software in my future career.</p>
<p><img decoding="async" loading="lazy" alt="Error getting image" src="https://ecase6.github.io/erin-ui-portfolio2/assets/images/dragQueen-51b82ed5ee52f50aeea7a595953b8966.jpeg" width="3484" height="2325" class="img_ev3q"></p>]]></content:encoded>
            <category>FreeForm</category>
            <category>DOET</category>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Affordances & Signifiers I]]></title>
            <link>https://ecase6.github.io/erin-ui-portfolio2/blog/affordancesAndSignifiersI</link>
            <guid>https://ecase6.github.io/erin-ui-portfolio2/blog/affordancesAndSignifiersI</guid>
            <pubDate>Tue, 03 Sep 2024 14:30:00 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[In response to Chapter 1 of: Norman, D.A. (2013). The design of everyday things. MIT Press.]]></description>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p><em>In response to Chapter 1 of: Norman, D.A. (2013). The design of everyday things. MIT Press.</em></p>
<p>I would summarize the section titled "Complexity of Modern Devices" with the word "human".</p>
<p><strong>“We have to accept human behavior the way it is, not the way we would wish it to be.”</strong></p>
<p>This is very relevant to remember when creating software and testing, along with creating everyday products like washing machines or blenders. It's important to keep humans behavior, understanding, and potential error in mind. It made me think about how elderly people are often blamed for their struggles with technology, but really they're just human, and it's not their fault that it's difficult for them to understand. When things are poorly designed, human error is inevitable (as the author alludes to this in his experience at the American nuclear power plan accident). I'll definitely remember this concept going forward, as I aim to design well and not get frustrated over "human error". There will always be room to improve and create a better and more clear experience for users.</p>
<p><img decoding="async" loading="lazy" alt="Error getting image" src="https://ecase6.github.io/erin-ui-portfolio2/assets/images/computerHelp-5e9b76c65835bda34c5c25fa97b5cca4.jpg" width="6100" height="4067" class="img_ev3q"></p>]]></content:encoded>
            <category>WordJournal</category>
            <category>DOET</category>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Example Blog Post]]></title>
            <link>https://ecase6.github.io/erin-ui-portfolio2/blog/example-blog-post</link>
            <guid>https://ecase6.github.io/erin-ui-portfolio2/blog/example-blog-post</guid>
            <pubDate>Mon, 26 Aug 2024 14:30:00 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[This is an example of a blog post for a homework assignment with an assigned reading.]]></description>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>This is an example of a blog post for a homework assignment with an assigned reading.
Lorem ipsum dolor sit amet, consectetur adipiscing elit, sed do eiusmod tempor incididunt ut labore et dolore magna aliqua. Ut enim ad minim veniam, quis nostrud exercitation ullamco laboris nisi ut aliquip ex ea commodo consequat. Duis aute irure dolor in reprehenderit in voluptate velit esse cillum dolore eu fugiat nulla pariatur. Excepteur sint occaecat cupidatat non proident, sunt in culpa qui officia deserunt mollit anim id est laborum.</p>]]></content:encoded>
            <category>FreeForm</category>
        </item>
    </channel>
</rss>